噉樣。
人比較多。
心只有柄。
係啊，馬逢國議員。
大家好，新年快樂！
誒，當局會以電腦投影片嘅形式去介紹。
我排隊又係嘅。我放個禮拜六就中意，所以即係大家啲。
好，咁首先誒，請當局就文件作出簡單嘅介紹啊！唔該。
咁首先係歡迎當局同埋西九管理局嘅代表出席會議。
時間有限，我長話短説，快快咁按英文彙報一下。
給他們一 chance to see exactly what we're talking about today. I'd like to introduce my colleagues, and they will take us through the presentation. All right, please do.
嘅啦，咁以前嘅第二項係西九文化區嘅文化軟件發展，咁請誒有關嘅政府當局同埋西九管理局嘅代表入場，唔該。
好誒，多謝咁多位委員，我哋而家夠鍾又夠人啦。咁會議議程嘅第一項，自上次會議後發出嘅資料文件，喺上次會議後發出嘅資料文件咧，已經再列於議程上邊。委員如果冇其他意見咧，我哋跟住落嚟就處理西九文化區嘅文化軟件發展。
也 looked at these important developments of capacity building to cultivate and nurture local talents.
我會快速 brief the highlights. The details are of course in the papers that members have all received.
和近30種不同的戲劇都被在第一年開幕時呈現，以展示這藝術形式的多樣性和豐富性。
Internship program continues and our Shizu Center docent program. We had almost 1,000 applicants for 100 docents to lead in English, Cantonese and Mandarin tours of the Shizu building.
had more than almost fourteen thousand audiences coming over the weekend of this inaugural jazz fest, so the audience delivery has been incredibly strong and fruitful in our first year of Shichu Center and first half year of Free Space.
誒主席，誒各位議員早晨。誒西九管理局咧喺上一次嘅聯合小組委員會會議咧，向委員會匯報咗西九文化區嘅硬件發展。啊，咪小長，我對近啲噉。好，好啊，好啊。誒主席，各位議員早晨。咁咧，西九管理局喺上一次嘅會議咧，就向大家介紹咗西九。
文化區硬件嘅發展啦，咁誒隨住啲硬件係嘅措誒嘅設施係陸續落成咧，而家西九管理局咧加緊發展緊文化嘅軟件，咁包括係積極推推動文化嘅交流合作啦，咁亦都係促進專業嘅發展，包括咧係為年青人咧係提供更加多發展同埋參與嘅機。
或者我請誒發展局嘅總裁阿柏志高先生再講解，再深入介紹。Please, thank you, Mr. Chairman. I'm actually not going to say anything myself in the interest of time, except to extend an invitation to all members to come and join the site visit next Monday morning, which will give.
Happy New Year! It is a tremendous pleasure to report on the previous year, 2019. Our ordinance indicates that West Kowloon's mission is to facilitate Hong Kong's long-term development as an international arts and cultural metropolis. And over the last year, I'm very honoured today to share how we've been doing just that.
for capacity building, the ordinance states we are here to cultivate and nurture local talents and facilitate the development of cultural and creative industries. Some of the highlights of programmes we've done to ensure we deliver this include programmes that work with theatre, dance, music and Shizu artists from throughout Hong.
Hong Kong in programmes that are now in their third and fourth year of delivery. What is stage looks at set design and stage design. We work with architects, stage designers and theatre practitioners, bringing in world-renowned artists such as Anna V. Brock to share her expertise with the local artists. What is art school with Edward.
Lam Dance Theatre from right here in Hong Kong provided a number of film screenings and discussions about the creative process of making Chinese language musicals for new artists and audiences working together, as well as for students coming to partner. Dramaturgy and Beyond is a partnership with Hong Kong Academy of Performing Arts that also
We also are working not just with the artists, but with the arts managers. Our Executive Lab short courses partnered with RADA and the University of the Arts London to use artistic practice to train public speaking, as well as other projects with non-arts practitioners, but people from the corporate world. So we're using skills from the arts.
World to reach out to even broader industries and programmes. Our Young Fellows Scheme is supporting new leaders in arts management to develop programmes that help support new community outreach engagement programmes. So, the first two fellows were chosen in 2019. One uses theatre to help train.
yes.
Miss Raphael.
多謝。
I don't know why it's got the Hong Kong Palace Museum up there.
Okay, thank you, Miss Friedman. Next one is by
popular both with the public, with tourists as well as with the docents themselves who love giving these tours every single day, and workshops at the Shichu Centre which enhance and further deepen appreciation of Shichu culture.
Our community, including at the bottom there, we dance was recognised by the Hong Kong Dance Alliance as one of the leading, as the best community engagement programme of this past year.
《廣》 observing the valley， also we found out just in the last couple days won an award in its premiere in Beijing this past fall. So we're very proud of these new works that are helping to develop a new generation of shi qu works and as well as spread the art form.
所以，總結， nurturing local talents, developing new works, encouraging wider participation of the arts. 二零一九已經是一個非常豐收的年份，來發展和確保香港的未來作為一個國際藝術和文化大都會，這就是西九龍的目的。謝謝。
Minority communities in Hong Kong to learn Cantonese, and another works with accessibility programs so people with visual and hearing impairment to have more access to performances. And these programs will then be shared with other arts arts organizations throughout Hong Kong to help reach more audiences. And of course, our performing arts
Moving on to audience building, audience building for the ordinance. We are here to enhance the appreciation of a diverse and pluralistic range of the arts, and to develop new and experimental works in arts and culture. And we've been very busy in programmes that have developed and delivered a diverse appreciation.
I'm thrilled to. Many of you were there for the grand opening and opening season of the Shichu Centre. For the three-month opening season, we were at 100 capacity for the audiences. This presented world-class performances, the best of the best Shichu from the region, including in addition to a focus on Cantonese opera, we had Peking opera, Kunshu.
We've also presented on this slide. I'd like to highlight we have musical theatre, contemporary dance, drama as well as jazz. So this shows the diversity of the art forms that we are presenting in our works to help develop audiences. Again, to deliver our commitment through the ordinance to enhance the appreciation of a diverse and pluralistic range of the arts.
this also builds capacity of local artists because every single one of these programs also involved local Hong Kong artists performing, collaborating and doing workshops with the invited guests. In the bottom there you'll see Grammy winner Robert Glasper and on the right you'll see local performers of jazz performers in our festival that.
In addition, we're continuing our Teahouse Theatre experience. This is our flagship program that helps bring Shichu to new audiences and to develop new artists for the art of Shichu. These performers are in their 20s and 30s, and it allows the development of this art form into the next generation. The Shichu Center both pres
the best of the classics and brings it forward into the 21st century. I'm also very proud to share Farewell My Concubine, which has been touring quite extensively in 2019. It won a number of awards last year, and again this is part of our commitment to develop new and experimental works in arts and culture as per our ordinance. The second new production, When
Finally, moving into community involvement, our ordinance underscores our mission to enhance the appreciation of arts and culture, and to encourage wider participation by the local community in arts and culture, as well as to provide arts education to the local community. I'd like to flag that this has already been recognised by.
Additional community engagement programs include seminar on culture of ritual opera performance, which, as well as the Hong Kong Young Talent Cantonese Opera and Operatic Singing Gala. Again, this is ensuring that this classic art form is preserved and developed into the next generation, and that all communities have access to one of Hong.
Hong Kong's richest cultural heritages. We also, for our jazz fest, brought Smithsonian Jazz Masterworks Orchestra to Hong Kong, not just for performance, but to reach students. And you'll see some students performing on stage with these leading icons of the art form in our workshop, in the performance and workshop for students at the this past.
The DH Chen Foundation, of course, is a very important program for secondary schools. Every single Wednesday and Friday, two hundred secondary school students have an opportunity to see a Shichu Centre performance at the Teahouse Theatre, to have a tour of the building and to learn more about Chinese culture and Shichu heritage. The Screen Dance School program.
所以。
Okay.
唔好意思啊！
yeah yeah okay.
I will.
yes yes.
Okay, who will be the next one, Miss Ravel?
自己嘅員工做一啲嘅分享嘅，咁呢方面咧，我哋都會誒誒誒幫助到我哋誒我哋嘅人才培訓工作。
啊！各位好，我好簡單講一講啊。香港文化博誒故宮博物館誒，關於喺兩方面嘅工作，噉就包括咗人才培訓啦，同埋觀眾拓展。下一張唔該。
參與咗一個典雅藝博二零一九，噉我哋係有一個展館，係將我哋誒香港故宮嗰個誒理念啦，誒佢哋介紹畀觀眾參觀嘅。
策略咧、願景咧，做咗一個專題嘅報告。咁呢個誒誒活動係好成功，係有成八百幾嘅中外嘅館誒，即係個一個博物館嘅從業員咧係參與。
因為我哋會活動，噉啊，喺哋喺往後誒嘅日子咧，我哋都會有更加多嘅啲嘅開幕前嘅活動咧，係誒進一步去拓展觀眾啦，等故宮誒公眾多啲認識我哋香港故宮嗰個使命同埋願景嘅。噉我個報告就喺呢度，噉我哋交翻畀下一位我嘅同事。
program also is in its third year now, reaching more students to create and have their own voices in this exciting work of shi chou of excuse me of screen dance. And finally, our West Kowloon One Hundred Ones, which are free lectures to enhance appreciation and wider participation in the art forms, shi chou centred centre guided tours have continued very.
啊！去翻去翻係誒，我哋其實喺人才培訓嗰度咧，我哋會開展一個同故宮博物誒院合作一個訪問學者嘅計劃。喺明年咧，我哋會安排有三個佢哋一啲嘅研究員咧嚟我哋香港故宮文化博物館誒，同我哋開展一啲就翻一啲展覽嘅策展啦、研究啦，同我哋。
要 look at.
嗯。
finally.
Wikipedia。
因為， many of these interns now over the last four years have become M+ museum staff.
mentor young curators through what is the most important international art event to take place globally. We had over a hundred thousand visitors for that programme.
The docent program, as we move closer to opening, we have expanded the docents by 72 in 2019 to have 136 new docent volunteers in our program.
另一方面咧，我哋有三個咧，我哋喺開館前嘅啲嘅誒活動。咁大家都知道咧，香港故宮文化博物館會喺二零二二年年中開館。喺未來呢兩年咧，我哋會安排一啲開幕前一啲嘅活動，去誒拓展我哋嘅觀眾羣。咁第一個咧，我哋今年我哋做咗就喺十月份，我哋係。
咁第二個咧，我哋亦做咗一個喺今年啱啱做咗一個開幕前嘅活動咧，就係誒誒文化香港故宮文化博物館嘅館長咧，就出席咗一個好大型一啲嘅國際博物館嘅論壇，就係博物館高峯論壇。咁喺個會上邊咧，我哋誒都就翻香港故宮嗰個未來嗰個籌建啦，同埋一個。
咁最後一個咧，我哋嘅公眾拓展活動咧，就係我哋啱啱喺上個月所舉辦。我哋邀請咗故宮博物院嘅院長啊，黃旭東博士咧，同我哋有一個公開嘅嘅講座，就講述關於誒敦煌同埋故宮喺文化傳承上面嘅關係喺嗰度嘅。咁呢三個咧都係我哋喺誒未來我哋誒開館之前。
Great, thank you. So with M Plus, our cultural software development begins with capacity building, and for us, it's very, very important to develop scholarship as well as support creative expression. So the Design Trust Research Fellowship Programme just does just that.
高 level research being presented and given a fellowship to to work on key learnings on Hong Kong and the Greater Bay Area. With the Sig Prize, an inaugural exhibition prize that has been established now by MPlus, we are.
支持新工作，由來自大灣區的藝術家所創作。當然，能力建構包括我們如何發展未來的博物館工作者，以及我們的講解員。所以，能力建構包括一個實習計劃，我們非常非常重視。
Our audience building, of course, feeds from our actual programme that we do, which are supported by docents and interns, and our fellowship and prize. You can see at over 19, we had three exhibitions at the M+ Pavilion, including the end of.
The Yann Vau Naguchi for Yann Vau exhibition, the five artists sites encountered, and the inaugural Sig Prize. We also have a live art program which enhances and expands what contemporary visual culture means, and of course.
嗯。
係。
public as well.
And also, I wish to thank Mr. Pascoat for inviting us to visit.
啊！就每位四分鐘。咁首先請馬逢國議員。
And it's been an extremely popular programme for many of our colleague institutions joining us at during those presentations.
我哋有四位咧，就係啊報咗名嘅，就係我讀嗰同學字序：馬逢國、陳志全、吳永嘉、黃碧雲。
We also had Charlotte Says speaking here in Hong Kong about her presentations in Venice, as well as a forum where we looked where we spoke with all the other four artists who worked with us previously for Venice.
With that, I will hand back to the floor. Thank you. Sorry for being a bit late. As this is the first meeting in 2020, I wish everybody a very happy and constructive 2020.
Our collaborations and educational programmes, of course, continue. Implas Rover, which began in 2016, takes Implas's learning and interpretation team out into all.
the the district next Monday, we'll talk about it a little bit a little bit later. Thank you, Miss Friedman, Doctor Ng and Miss Rafael for your presentation. And now is question time.
Last year, we presented for the fourth time in partnership with the Hong Kong Arts Development Council, the Hong Kong Pavilion as part of the collateral events at Venice. A very, very successful presentation of Scholzé with curator Christina Lee. Again, we
Audience building continues, of course, with our screening programmes and our lectures and symposia. And like the Palace Museum, we invite a key lecture every year. And this time, Maria Balshaw, the director of Tate, presented 'Global Museums in Shifting Times'. We also work
work with other non-for-profits in Hong Kong to co-present important programmes, including the Wikipedia Editorthon, which we do with the Asia Art Archive every year now. And part of that programme is to expand the number of women artists that are visible through
Well, as we continue building our collection, we also make that collection available to the public through our M Plus Collections Beta. This is now over five thousand objects, and by the time we open the museum, we we expect to have the whole collection up there for people.
During Art Basel Hong Kong, we also presented M+ Human Library. In the lead-up to the opening of the museum, we wanted to introduce to Hong Kong audiences who M+ is, the staff, our special our specialists from conservation, framing, registration, curators, archivists, and so.
We also do talks and symposia and as an important underlying part of our programming. And the open up museum learning in the twenty first century is a series of talks, really there to expand on our docent training, but we open it up to all.
高級學校和社區中心，和現在這一年，我們會看小學學校。我們現在也有暑期營業校友，去年我們已經和那校友超過70位校友一起幫助我們準備和思考我們如何。
誒，多謝主席。誒，剛才聽咗即係西九嘅管理層嘅一啲報告啦，咁都好開心見得到咧，即係誒軟軟件方面咧，即係西九都逐步逐步咁發展，同埋即係誒開展緊。
係好豐富嘅，咁本身嚟講，究竟我哋會唔會係誒我哋香港故宮係可以全部做曬，亦或係我哋可以有啲嘅夥伴合作咧？咁喺往後咧，我哋都會積極探討呢啲嘅可能性嘅。啊，多謝啊，麥議員嘅問題。多謝，係啊，秘書長。
管去承接啊，定係繼續維持一種誒各自去運營嘅誒進行合作嘅狀態啊？定係有咩新嘅諗法嘅安排咧？呢一種噉嘅誒諗法嘅安排係咪已經進行當中咧？誒想即係誒可以回應下呢幾個問題。
嘅故宮文化博物館有冇考慮利用佢哋呢一啲展覽咧，係進行一啲合作？誒，起碼係配合到，譬如話，我哋香港故宮文化博物館喺開館之前嘅一個宣傳啦、推廣啦，咁咁甚至咧係進行一啲即係深度少少嘅交流。
structure our youth programmes into the future, and of course, access outreach is extremely important. And this and this time in 2019, we did some customised outreach programmes for um ex for particular accessibility audience.
誒喺呢度咧，我有一一兩個問題就想跟進嘅。第一個問題，我想跟進咧就係關於呢個誒故宮文化博物館。噉我哋大家都知道咧，喺目前咧正係喺呢個誒誒我哋嘅科學館咧，就故宮咧係正在進行緊一個展覽啦，由康文署主辦嘅。咁誒，即係我都注意到咧，其實。
誒康文署下嘅博物館咧，喺過去一段時間都誒不斷咁誒，係會利用佢嘅場地咧，係同故宮博物館咧係誒合作舉辦一啲展覽，去推廣故宮啦。噉我想了解一下咧，即係我哋嘅本身嘅香港故宮文化博物館咧，喺呢方。
方面誒同康文署有冇咩默契咧？因為誒，我睇唔到喺誒過去一段時間咧，由康文署主辦嘅嘅展覽咧，係有同我哋嘅故宮文化博物館咧有合作嘅。咁誒，其實呢啲係一啲好難得嘅機遇啦。咁誒，我哋嘅。
咁另外一個問題就係話誒，我哋點樣去準備？就係話當香港嘅故宮文化博物館正式落成啟用之後，誒康文署誒香港嘅故宮文化博物館同埋誒故宮博物院咧，到底嗰個未來嘅關係係點樣咧？係主要嘅工作係由呢個香港故宮文化博
多謝誒，邊邊位先回答咧？阿吳博士。啊，多謝阿阿馬議員嘅問題。噉就誒誒，過去嗰誒由二零一二年開始咧，康文署同故宮都有好多一啲合作項目推展咗，咁包括一啲嘅誒展覽咧，都好受誒市民嘅歡迎嘅。咁誒而家。
觀眾咧都有一個年輕化嘅趨勢，噉我想誒。
萎弱嘅電影戲棚咧，噉係咪係咪？我想知多少少啊嘛，係咪西九出資去去拍一一部噉嘅戲咁？
講嘅就係個小劇場，噉我自己都去過睇一次睇誒《霸王別姬》，咁但係都係一啲朋友即係介紹開啦，咁誒。
故宮博物館博物院嘅院長咧係會面嘅，咁所以我諗未來嘅歲月咧，因為已經有咗個上設嘅香港故宮博物館咧，我哋肯定咧係會多啲利用呢個場地誒去推介誒故宮嘅傳統文化。
做緊一個展覽，就係喺科學館做啦。咁以我所知道咧，誒明年年中咧都仲有一個展覽咧，就喺誒文化博物館去開展嘅。咁呢啲展覽咧，其實誒呢啲嘅展覽同埋佢相關一啲嘅教育活動啊、推廣活動咧，都對香港市民誒對古文化嗰個認識咧係好有幫助，亦係。
係，亦幫助到我哋一啲觀眾羣嗰個拓展嘅。咁以我所知道咧，誒暫時誒康文署同埋故宮嗰個誒展覽嗰個合作咧，就到出年開始。咁其實呢樣嘢就係正好就係可以接到我哋規劃中咧。其實我哋香港故宮喺開幕之前咧，會喺二零二一年咧。
都有一啲嘅誒大型嘅展覽咧，就會接住去去去舉辦。咁可以話咧，由過去嗰幾年一路到開香港故宮開展嘅時間咧，我哋誒香港市民都有機會可以睇到一啲誒香港同香港誒呢個北京故宮相關嘅文物啦，同埋一啲相關嘅展覽嘅。咁所以誒呢一方面。
咧，我哋會繼續，我哋會睇一睇，我哋由而家到開館誒嘅時間，點樣可以更一更加有效咁去開始我哋嘅觀眾嘅拓展。咁呢個就係回應阿馬議員第一個問題。咁至於第二個問題咧，誒呢方面咧就誒，我哋而家誒全年嘅工作都係誒做緊開館嘅工。
噉我哋其實開館除咗係嗰個硬件之外咧，我哋都開始我哋誒誒規劃我哋未來嘅軟件，包括咗我哋將來嘅展覽啦、我哋嘅觀眾拓展啦、我哋嘅教育推廣活動啦。噉我哋誒走翻我哋而家嚟講咧，都同董事局咧有一個好詳細嘅啲嘅計劃嘅。咁以將來呢個。
誒誒將來嘅合作咧，其實係牽涉到三方面咧。我哋香港故宮咧，誒北京故宮咧，同埋康文署本身嘅博物館咧。噉我哋誒積極都會睇一睇將來我哋呢三方入面嗰個合作，譬如我哋同誒康文署嘅故宮嘅合作喺，因為我哋都大家知道咧，香呢個北京故宮本身佢個文物資源。
多謝主席。好簡單喺三個方面，從個機制上去補充阿吳博士講嘅嘢。首先咧，喺誒香港文誒香港誒故宮博物館嘅董事局入邊咧，康文處長係一個成員嚟嘅。咁除咗康文處長之後咧，仲有兩位成員咧係曾經喺康文處一啲誒。
處理博物館嘅諮詢委員會係工作過嘅，咁所以換句話説咧，喺董事局入邊咧係有啲人咧好清楚康文署嘅工作嘅。而第二樣咧就係誒民政事務局作為係誒負責誒文化政策嘅咧，我哋亦都會協誒確保兩個協調嘅。誒，我舉個例舉兩個例子。
第一喺去年十二月咧，誒，我哋舉辦個亞洲文化論壇嘅，噉啊，黃旭東誒博士咧係係一個邀請嘅嘉賓之一啦。咁喺嗰度咧，誒就住阿黃旭東博士嚟到嘅時候咧，誒西九管理局同康文署都合作咗，有一啲活動咧喺康文署搞，有一啲係西九搞嘅。
噉我哋大家咧都會係誒互相通傳同埋係誒宣傳嘅。第三咧就係話其實去年誒大家都知道誒康文署長係誒新嘅康文署長上任啦。當佢去北京做禮節性拜訪嘅時候咧，其實我哋亦都邀請咗吳志華博士咧係一起同新嘅康文署長同新嘅。
親自住院醫院。啊，唔該，主席。主席，今日我哋討論嘅係誒西九文化區嘅文化軟件發展啦。咁即係我哋去抌咗咁多錢、咁多心機去發展西九文化區。我諗大家嗰個對西九嘅期望就唔單止係多咗表演場地或者展覽嘅場地呢啲硬件嘅。係當然。
硬件係要好好運用啦，噉係每個期望咧會係多過多個表演場地。噉我特別想畀意見係關於戲曲嘅發展啦。咁戲曲中心就係最先投入誒服務嘅一個場地啦。咁呢個場地當然好靚，誒好多業界都話不識宮本都要。
去試一次噉樣，所以第頭嗰一一兩年咧，我諗嗰個誒使用啊、誒租用啊嗰啲都唔唔使點樣去擔心啊。但係因為如果純粹講一個場地提供者，噉佢係好被動嘅，即係睇下有冇人嚟租場啊，嗰啲戲係好唔好啊噉樣噉佢。
ok。
oh，sorry。
Hello.
邊位回答？
Miss Friedman。
啊，鍾鍾女士。
呢個方向係咪都係你哋其中一個，即係提供多啲軟件嘅誒未來嘅誒路線咧？咁唔該。
只不過係同誒第啲場表演場地去做一個競爭，咁反而嗰個軟件咧，我係誒關心嘅。我哋成日都講緊誒拓展觀眾羣喺粵劇上咧，要拓展觀眾羣咧係誒困難嘅，但係近年咧都各方面都好努力啦。即係我見到啲無論係表演者啦，定係觀。
係一個咁細嘅場地，即係可能誒二百百零二百人，好近距離去接觸到，直頭睇到佢哋嘅表情啊，即係同埋同啲樂師個距離都好近咧。咁呢個呢個經驗係好好特別嘅，我覺得都好好珍貴。噉我希望誒未來可以運用多啲，同埋嗰個誒。
誒劇目會多啲，因為而家我哋見到有《霸王別姬》，《霸王別姬》咪呢四隻字都可以吸引到大家入去睇，即係想睇下咩一回事。但係譬如未來《文廣探谷》，咁如果就咁睇呢四個字，我又未必未必會純粹去吸引到我我入場去睇，咁個宣傳係重要啦。同埋我想知誒，譬如《霸王》。
別機呢個嗰個係咪即係等於係西九做班主？你哋去搞一啲誒呢啲小劇場噉，如果係嘅話，咁嗰個版權係係係西九嘅咧。如果如果有如果係或者如果你攞到嘅話，其實呢一啲噉嘅精彩表演咧都可以多加利用嘅，即係譬如。
嗯，出版啊，或者一啲片段放喺網嗰度，我覺得都可以令到更多人可以接觸到粵劇，同埋睇到原來係佢又比較易入口，因為唔係一場一場好好長嘅戲啦，同埋嗰啲老觀戲其實你都你又貴啦，即係對於新觀眾嚟講，亦都你。
有錢都未必買到飛，係嘛噉，所以誒，從呢啲小劇場係去做入門，我覺得係係誒應該多加嘗試嘅。而家嗰個數量好似就係咪少啲咧？即係你個小劇場喺度，但係誒只係得一個劇目。另外，我想問就係第三十四段講嗰部。
誒主席，誒陳議員，多謝你嘅提問嘅。咁誒其實誒講翻頭先《霸王別姬》先，《霸王別姬》咧就係我哋自己誒戲曲中心誒製作嘅一個作品嚟嘅。咁誒如果講到版權方面咧，噉就誒要睇下，因為咧其實作家嘅版權，即係個編劇版權，梗係歸。
編劇嘅，但係我哋誒擁有誒一定年份嘅誒嗰個版權嘅，咁但係演出版權仍然都係我哋誒西九自己擁有嘅。咁誒另外文廣探谷方面咧，誒多謝你嘅意見，我哋誒翻去都會諗下個名嘅。咁因為呢個都係楊家將嘅故事嚟嘅嚇，咁誒因為香港咧。
咧就未演過，噉我哋就會誒嚟緊嘅誒二零二零年十月份咧都會喺香港會再演嘅。噉我哋中間呢段時間咧會再打磨下呢一個戲。雖然我哋喺北京首演咗，咁誒另外咧就係呢個呢一個戲咧，亦都係我哋自己誒中心做製作嘅，同埋誒全部都係。
我覺得。
Mr. Prescott.
Thank you, Kingsley。黃碧雲議員。
We're being a little bit excessive in what we do, so the whole focus is very much on empowering the customer, allowing them to personalise their journeys and really, really give them that control.
有冇相關嘅考慮到相關嘅做法，加入類似嘅技術，從而可以好啲咁掌握到文件裏邊所講嘅更深入瞭解觀眾嘅興趣、需要同埋習慣咧？
about the data security and the amount of data we hold, we're particularly looking within the museum about how we can monitor people's movement through the museum, not as individuals, but really understanding general trends of movement, so their dwell time, the amount of time they spend, but encouraging them
present moment is to use the established technology to to gather information about our audience, about visitors to the site. So we're not we're not looking, for example, at facial recognition. We don't think that's appropriate for the type of operation that we're doing. But perhaps Kingsley can explain some of the the thinking that we.
我哋自己誒誒邀請設計師啊去諗啊，同埋誒嗰個誒全部嘅製作都係我哋噉。但係我想講翻咧，就係嗰個小劇場嘅地方啦。咁誒，大家嚟睇小劇場誒呢一個藝術節嘅時候咧，嗰個地方其實本身係我哋嘅一號排練室嚟嘅。我哋今年因為啱啱開幕咧，所以
所以我哋就想試下咧，將一個一號訓練室咧，將佢誒，因為佢又夠大啊。噉我哋咧就每年咧就將佢變成一個創作嘅基地。咁因為我哋小劇場藝術節咧邀請嘅誒誒團體咧，多數咧嗰啲誒戲咧都係全部全新再編過啦，或者係誒重新打磨過嘅。咁
誒，全部咧都係一啲年青嘅朋友或者年青人，或者第啲團隊嘅年青嘅誒梯隊咧去做呢一啲誒小劇場嘅誒誒實驗劇噉樣咯。咁所以咧誒就唔誒平日咧，因為我哋都誒要排練啦，利用嗰個地方，所以就唔可以誒成日都做。
咗個小劇場噉，只不過可以每年咧改裝噉樣咯，改裝兩個月噉樣。噉我哋嚟緊二零二零年咧都會橫跨誒由九月中至到十二月咧都有呢個小劇場展演嘅。咁希望咧能夠鼓勵多啲咧新嘅創作同埋誒一啲誒，好似陳議員話比較容易入口嘅誒，用嚟做呢一
個觀眾拓展噉樣咯，咁誒至於呢個戲棚嗰個誒電影方面咧，誒都係我哋戲曲中心誒全資誒去拍攝嘅一個紀錄片嘅原因咧，就係當初就知道誒，因為我哋二零一二年到一四年嘅時候做過西九大戲棚啦，當時咧已經誒知道。
咧嗰個戲棚誒搭建嗰度咧，會係比較誒，即係再遲多幾年咧，可能誒有機會傳承唔到。噉我哋希望咧用誒影片嚟誒記錄低佢，然之後係誒傳承嘅作用。至少我哋下一代可能睇到誒有一啲紀錄片，知道原來有戲棚可以搭。
嘅噉樣噉，所以呢一個咧，我哋都會誒喺二月份啦，或者誒誒稍後誒今年咧都會再誒放映嘅。咁希望就將呢一個誒誒大型嘅手工藝啦，同埋誒一個香港好重要嘅誒一個誒文化係留低落嚟。
好誒，跟住吳永嘉議員，我都係主席誒，我都係想就住文件六十一段關於香港故宮文化博物館嘅嘅軟件方面嘅發展嘅噉。文件提到咧，為咗等訪客得到最佳嘅博物館經驗啦，係體驗香港故宮博物館咧就。
設計計劃進行研究，更深入咁瞭解觀眾嘅興趣、需要同埋習慣。噉我就想問下啦，其實而家都帶入咗數碼年代好多好多年㗎啦。噉啊，我理解到咧，台灣咧係有啲博物館咧已經咧實地應用咗一種其實都好耐嘅叫做Bacon嘅低功耗嘅藍牙。
技術咧就可以準確咁將入場嘅觀眾定位，然後咧就收集咗同埋分析佢嘅大數據，等博物館可以瞭解到嘅參觀者咧嘅遊覽路線，或者佢哋中意特別中意邊一類展品，同埋佢哋嘅興趣。咁唔知局方或者係西九文化中心有？
Just to supplement, I think that we we are looking at that technology, but clearly we we need to be very careful about privacy, we need to be very careful about data collection and storage and handling. So we're looking at the procedural side as well as the practical side. Practically, our preference at
呢啲嘅效益。
噉就誒，跟住我想問一問咧，嗰個誒軟件嘅問題。
或者個表現係點樣樣嘅？因為我哋其實係睇唔到你哋定嗰個目標係乜嘢嘢。
Mr. Prescott, Mr. Chairman, I think I need to make a couple of things clear on this one. First, it's not our responsibility to pay workers employed by a company.
即係我哋，我哋而家睇唔到嗰個目標。誒，我哋唔知道你而家做呢啲嘢咧，到即係對嗰個實際嘅需求係距離幾遠嘅。
事嘅噉樣，即係咁咁邊個係負責最後問責嘅咧？咁咁誒，即係我希望係呢一班工人嘅誒欠薪嘅問題，儘快可以處理到。
究竟其實佢哋拖咗三個月，究竟係有涉及幾多工人係冇糧出啦？涉及金額係幾多啦？同埋而家幫佢哋追翻呢啲薪酬嘅進展嘅情況係點啦？同埋呢班工人有冇優先獲聘用，繼續完成相關嘅工程？
就誒，我哋睇到咧，其實呢度都誒西九畀咗好多，即係佢哋做咗啲乜嘢啊？喺即係話話畀我哋聽噉啊！多謝你哋嘅報告。不過似乎我哋其實係誒議員或者公眾係冇辦法去判斷到。
我哋完全冇嗰啲誒key performance indicator，亦都唔知道應該定一個目標係幾多先夠。譬如你話實習生誒，我哋每年大專實實習生有三十人，咁其實三十人又係咪足夠咧？
誒又或者導賞員嗰度誒第二十三段，你講咧就係話已經招募到一百三十六個導賞員啦。噉我想問，即係你哋預期當呢一個嘅誒西九開嘅時候，其實你係需要amplis需幾多導賞員咧？
In terms of the technology, I mean one of the key points that we're doing is that we have a a centralised CRM system, which means that we're collecting data on customers wherever throughout the district. It means we're able to follow their behaviour from venue to venue, gain insights from that. We're looking at how we can personalise content through them for them through
Their emails through their website, presents and things like that. So we're able to give targeted data, and this is going to really, really help benefit because we'll understand as people engage with us through the C2C centre, through M Plus, through HKPM, more about their behaviours. But as Mr. Peskett mentioned, we are very conscious.
Under their own control to interact with information, so asking people to engage with artworks, whether it's through QR codes or other things like that. So the whole principle is the fact that the customer feels in control of their data, because we are a bit worried that people may feel that if we collect a large amount of data, they may feel that we're
誒主席，就誒我哋而家係討論嗰個文化軟件啦，西九噉，但係硬件同軟件都有關係。噉我首先想跟進下，就誒Amphas嗰邊嗰個誒工程嘅進展咧，係咪會如期誒順利係可以進行到啦？咁
因為誒早前我哋聽到咧就係誒Amphas博物館嘅水喉同埋風喉工程嘅小型分判商嗰度理德噉係你哋中止咗同佢嘅合約嘅噉，我想問咧就即係誒西九已經唔係第一次係誒即係拖數嚇工人係冇出糧嘅噉，我想問今次。
公司responsibility. What we have to do is to ensure that the company pays the workers, and it became evident that they were not getting their wages in a suitable manner. Hence, we took action. We then followed up with the labour department to ensure that those workers that had not been paid were paid. And I can say that.
Thank you for the.
謝偉權議員。
The details, perhaps, Sahani, you can comment on the M+ situation.
these these continue as part of our ongoing audience building, capacity building.
喺佢落成嘅時候，我哋而家仲爭幾多？係需要跑幾多數啊！即係我想，我想即係問就係一個噉嘅問題。
Architects in Hong Kong and the region, and we worked with Hong Kong University to to develop that. And we do one keynote every year at the end.
The latest information I had, I think it's about 120 workers. I can't give you the details separately. We have resolved all but two as of December 25th. I don't know what the exact position is today. I assume that the last two members, and I know the reason that we were not able to resolve those claims.
for payment were that they could not provide sufficient information regarding their attendance at the worksite, and that's the only requirement we have. I can say that for every worker who enters the worksite, they do have a palm print, so we know exactly when they enter and when they leave. But there are occasionally discrepancies.
as to whether they left early or left late, so that's the issue that affected, as as I understood it, as of the end of December, two workers. I will check exactly what that is and get back to the honourable member with more details separately. 啊，主席，當然我知道唔係直接由阿柏志高生出糧畀嗰啲水喉工人啦，咁但係即係
新窗同埋而家負責嘅金門咧，其實佢哋係誒作為誒幫手睇住呢一個工程。噉佢哋如果發出去分判商嗰度，分判商唔出糧，噉我諗成個監管系統係出現問題嘅，因為已經係一而再、再而三出現嘅呢個情況。我相信你唔可以話下邊下邊唔出糧唔關我。
咁所以，我我相信呢一紮嘢咧，其實都應該要有一個清晰啲嘅目標。譬如今年你又打算recruit幾多個導賞員咧？係需要recruit幾多個實習生咧？誒，你打算有幾多場嘅相關嘅講座或者節目，係培養到幾多嘅人才咧？即係。
呢一啲，我哋而家完全都誒冇喺手度，噉我哋係睇唔到你其實係做得幾好，你已經超標啦，做得好好啦，抑或其實你仲佢哋嘅目標係好遠咧噉。噉我諗我哋需要一個清晰一啲嘅圖畫，由而家距離每一個主要嘅誒表演場地或者博物館或者故宮。
Mr. Peskott, briefly on the KPI issues. In fact, we have drafted KPIs for each of the divisions, and we did a pilot scheme two years ago, which we're now reviewing, and it will in future be part of our annual report. So that information will be made public. So that's that's something we already have in place. As far as
It's okay, we can hear you. Yeah, it's working now. The interns, the interns programme is is part of a broader West Kowloon District internship programme, and the museum interns ten every year as part of its ongoing work, and we have been doing that this now for a number of years.
With the hope that we can convert them into M plus staff, and we've been very successful at that. And we continue to do those ten internships within the museum. We have an additional twelve interns that we put in place for our Venice Biennale every two years, and we do that with.
機構方面係呢方面嘅一啲品牌嚇，唔該主席。
啊！我哋都睇到同埋聽到啦，過去一年。
係誒香港個芭蕾舞團啊，即係香港舞蹈團啊，同埋城市當代舞團。
噉啊，最後我都有個問題想問一問嘅，就係喺文件裏邊同埋正話三位介紹。
Our own expertise. We also engage leaders from Hong Kong APA and other dance sector establishment to work with us to help select those participating artists.
Mr. Peskov, I think this is a very good question because I, I personally dislike just signing agreements that say we'll work together. I really feel it's important that we have a deliverable and some measurable targets to work towards. So that's what we're trying to do with all of our agreements. So perhaps Alison can explain exactly what we're doing.
香港 arts development council again a very important international forum for young people in Hong Kong to get training around including technical training and that continues as well so we reach our target every time it's important for members to know that the internship program
are paid interns and that's that's very important for us that we pay our young our young interns in regard to docents we will look to have 200 docents in place these are volunteers but we we train them as as as they come online and
We prepare them for the opening using our M Plus Pavilion as the place to train that those those volunteers, so that they get to interact with school audiences, general public audiences, special accessibility audiences, according to the exhibition.
In terms of talks and lecture and symposium programmes, we do a minimum of three M plus matters a year, and we often work with universities. So we've just done a very important programme looking at women.
係，多謝主席。誒，當然咧，西九文化區咧，即係我哋做咗咁耐咧，大家對誒西九文化區方面咧，即係有個期望嘅。咁亦都希望喺呢方面咧，可以幫到我哋誒香港啊，同埋即係市民方面喺呢方面咧，喺文化方面嘅一啲未來。
嘅發展同埋係喺呢方面多啲選擇欣賞，亦都提升咗即係香港即係好多時候就作為即係呢個誒一個大都會方面喺文化方面嘅呢方面嘅即係選擇同埋嗰個誒欣賞嗰個水平。噉啊，即係我我其實主要我注意文。
件裏邊咧就係誒，其實誒管理局咧，其實都係同本地同埋一啲海外嘅藝團咧，其實有簽署一啲即係協議啊，三年嘅咁誒，即係或者一啲安排咧，從而等佢哋可以提供一啲呢方面嘅藝術嘅節目啦。噉啊，包括咧裏邊都有講過咧，即係。
亦都有啲誒其他國家嘅，包括喺法國啊，或者英國啊等等嘅唔同嘅誒藝團嘅。噉啊呢方面咧，其實即係當然係可以係誒令到我哋喺呢個選擇方面咧更加多，咁亦都使到本地嘅藝團有多啲喺呢方面嘅機會去表演。
咁喺呢度嚟講咧，就係我都想問，即係喺簽署呢度，即係呢啲有關安排咧。其實而家其實係唔係即係一路做緊？咁其實有幾多咧喺呢方面揀選？有冇揀選嘅一啲誒基本客觀考慮嘅條件或者因素咧？咁呢第一樣嘢，第二樣嘢咧。
誒，我唔知有冇咧，即係喺呢方面咧推動一下本地啊，本地藝團同埋國際唔同國家藝團喺呢方面合作，從而咧即係希希望西九咧佢喺呢方面咧有啲誒獨特嘅，即係話香港本地啊，同埋誒唔同國家嘅噉啊，打造一啲即係喺。
咁誒。
咁唔同嘅形式。
多數都係依班人啊！
咁亦都可能咧，即係。
整個西港文化區。
其實都有好多豐富嘅活動嘅。
一定要重質，但係亦都要重量。
同唔同唔同類型嘅活動都有。
啊！我估計唔同嘅項目咧，都有一套衡量嘅方式。
因為有時咧，可能係同一班藝術嘅愛好者，個個活動都會參加。
有陣時，社會大眾未必完全知道每一個項目佢個獨特嘅地方。
令到出嚟嘅參加人人人次數啦，嚇未必一次㗎，佢哋有好多嘅。
啊！參與嘅人數啊，參與者嘅滿意程度等等嘅，噉我亦都建議咧，誒西九文化局咧可以加強My West Kowloon會員制嘅功能。
即係我亦都明白到咧，藝藝術活動咧，有時係好單單用人數去平衡或做作為一個指標嘅。咁當然藝術嘅嘢，我覺得咧。
咁誒，因為誒，例如係係咪可以用手機應用程式咧？誒，可以報名啊、參加啊、填寫問題啊、畀意見啊。誒，亦我覺得亦都可以咧，用呢個方法畀到誒。
當局統計，除咗參加人數之外咧，唔同類別嘅參與人數有幾多？佢哋認為項目嘅質素啊係點樣等等，或者佢哋有啲咩新嘅要求啊、改改善、改良啊等等。
Thank you very much. Thank you, Chairman. Thank you for your question. As Duncan mentioned, the partnerships are about long-term investment in the Hong Kong ecology and creating multi-step opportunities to build bridges and provide resources and opportunities for the local groups. The three flagship companies you mentioned.
The criteria for those organisations, those partnerships, were with an eye to the development of the Lyric Theatre Complex, which will open our next venue to open, which will be a dance house, Hong Kong's newest centre for excellence in dance. And we are looking at having resident companies at the Lyric Theatre Complex. So.
Starting early to work with the companies to understand their needs and their development in anticipation of that building opening was the goal and the underlying mission for partnerships there. And we're able to use free space now that it's open as a trial platform for some of those partnerships there.
For the international MOU that you mentioned, including the UK, Finland, Australia and many more, those are targeting the independent sector to ensure that independent artists, emerging artists, less established, have opportunities to grow, to create, to be inspired and to.
也發展他們自己的能力，作為專業人士在業界。那些是透過一係數個階段，涉及專業人士喺香港嘅藝術業界，嚟睇申請，嚟睇佢哋嘅標準，佢哋嘅使命係乜嘢，藝術家係咪準備好喺嗰個下一步嘅發展。所以喺除咗
Kingston。
噉我都想聽聽誒。
Yes, absolutely. Customer feedback is very, very
events. We also do surveys within the theatre.
啊，Mr. Pearsant, Mr. Jim, and I'll start, and then I'll pass on to Kingsley.
啊，有一啲活動啊，可以用咩方式去調整啊，等等。
The other thing that we're doing is we obviously obviously monitor our social media for comments and respond to those.
Not just the performance programmes, but some of the back of house programmes. You mentioned particularly, you know, use of technology, mobile apps and what have you. And indeed, we are looking at that. And perhaps Kingsley could comment on that for me.
股誒update嘅資料畀我哋嚇，作於誒有一啲譬如修改又好，或者係改進又好，或者新加入嘅項目又好啊，我想聽聽你哋響呢一方面有啲咩嘅睇法。
會唔會因為噉樣樣即係變得一個小眾咧？咁但係我聽到嘅咧，而家即係好多人都好期待啊，譬如喺西九裏邊嘅啊，故宮博物館啊，等等其他嗰啲活動，正話亦都有議員提到。
啊！西九文化局喺依一方面有咩睇法，同埋即係點樣可以嗱？我我哋依個委員會唔係micro manage要你哋你你哋依個依個西九文化局嘅，但係我哋係需要啊！你響適時咧，畀一啲好。
Membership schemes are actually very, very important for arts institutions. We already have a prototype membership scheme for M+. We're working on similar ones for the performing arts side, situe dance and what have you. And in due course, of course, as the Palace Museum opens, we'll have membership schemes there. We'll also be
looking at a district-wide approach because I think there are specialist areas and then there are general areas. We need to cover both. So I think you're absolutely right. It's a very good opportunity for us to get to know our audiences better. We can offer them benefits from being involved in membership, but we can also involve them more in some of our programmes.
Already instituted a process of post-event questionnaires, so when the public come to a show and their ticket is scanned, automatically an email is sent to them which asks them for their feedback, and we've done this very successfully with the Tea House Theatre. We got some very very useful feedback there, and we're doing this of course more and more of.
And we're also just started by having a annual sentiment survey. So this is a Hong Kong wide survey asking people's opinions, awareness of the project and how they feel about it. So we get a judgement of people who aren't necessarily coming to the district yet to understand what they feel and expect from it. We will have
For our app, feedback that people can give, and engagement that we can do, and also, as Mr. Peskett mentioned, we're starting work on a district-wide loyalty scheme. And the idea behind this scheme is it not only covers the types of membership run by MPlus or C Two Centre, but works across every.
其他元素。
方式誒。
電信嘅方式又好。
誒誒，依個劇。
如如果可以用一啲誒，
O.K.咁誒，依個。
睇下用一啲咩形式，事前。
to to actually kind of measure their engagement.
劇嘅背景嘅，噉我覺得，如果響呢一方面可以。
因為對於一啲好文化好有深厚認識嗰啲咧，佢去到咧就。
一啲軟件嘅方式又好，介紹一下誒一啲展覽品，或者一啲表演嘅項目。
依個誒，譬如戲曲戲曲中心睇個粵劇噉樣咧，我都想知道多一啲有關嘅展品或者依個。
sorry，我哋完咗啦。依個係啦，噉我哋而家咧就我哋會進入去下一個項目。下一個項目咧就係誒西九文化區場地營運。
差唔多乜都知㗎啦。但係我自己去博物館有好多，我就睇佢靚唔靚啊啊！咁但係響睇佢靚唔靚，響欣賞依件藝術品或者嗰個。
including the park, the F and B, all those different elements, allowing people to generate points that can be used, and some of those points be generated not just because they buy tickets, but because of activities they do, for example, volunteering.
你睇睇先。
謝秘書長。
進度嘅彙報。
亦都請誒。
好。
咁或者誒？
Again, I'll pass on to my colleagues in Egypt.
政府同埋西九嘅代表首先作出誒一啲介紹啦，係咪啊？
噉啊，或者我哋請有關嘅西九代表。
咁如果大家係週末去睇下咧，就知道咧，其實呢個已經變成係市民閒時休憩、放鬆嘅新熱點，我哋所謂嘅打卡點。
去多一啲介紹嘅咧，即係對於我哋香港市民一啲唔係對文化藝術有咁深厚認識嗰啲咧，即係好有幫助㗎嚇。咁都都希望你哋去可以喺呢方面啊留意一下嚇。
I'm afraid, in some cases, unfortunately, our audience, visitors and tenants, and of course our staff members, have been affected by major traffic disruption. And as a consequence, some shows and programmes have had to be rescheduled, or indeed, occasionally cancelled.
首兩個表演場地，即係戲曲中心同埋自由空間，喺去年啟用咧。其實西九文化區咧已經有一個項目規劃同埋建造嘅階段咧，邁向營運嘅階段啦。誒，而且咧，我哋下邊咧係藝術公園同埋海濱長廊，亦已經分階段開放。秘秘書長，可可能嗰個口。
有個問題，你可唔可以講大聲少少？好好好，誒主席誒，隨住西九首兩座嘅表演場地、戲曲中心同埋自由空間咧，去年啟用咧，其實西九已經由一個係誒規劃同埋建造嘅階段，邁去一個營運嘅階段啦。另外咧，我留意到建藝術公園同埋海濱長廊咧，亦都係分階段開放。
管理局咧係會密切檢視營運情況同埋模式，誒希望係能夠繼續誒提升個設施同埋服務質素，亦都係更好地服務市民同埋提供更多元化嘅機會咧，等公眾欣賞同埋享受佢藝術節目嘅。咁或者我而家就請西九管理局啊，柏志高先生同埋佢同事。
Keeping the the time as succinct as we can. Two things I want to say. This of course has been a milestone year with opening of essentially three venues if we include the art park, free space and the C2 centre. The the challenges we've had quite honestly in delivering world class venues have have been those challenges that
Hong Kong generally faces the disruption that has been caused by the situation on the on the streets has had an effect, and we've had to work very hard to keep the programming going. We've had the ideology of the show must go on, so as far as possible, we've tried to make sure that our venues are open and the programme.
嗯。
And these have been very well received.
The facilities work and what our future plans should be.
I'd like to invite my colleagues to take us through the presentation, if I may. Please, who will be next?
Authority's in-house ticketing has enabled us to provide timely communication to ticket holders.
And the policy covers both hardware and software, because it's very, very important that we see these two aspects linked together, all the time.
Space events, we've done work to encourage people to allow wheelchair users to be able to access the lawns. So there's a wide variety of areas that we're trialling.
meetings about accessibility, particularly referring to the development of the hardware. But in 2016, we took a step forward by establishing a dedicated accessibility team.
Another initiative we tried is portable service bells for the audience. They can take these into the auditorium. If they need any assistance, they press the button, and our ushers can come and assist them during the show.
And key to this is the participation of people with visual impairments in design processes for touch tours, access tours, trying to make sure that people are involved in these processes as much as possible.
And in 2018, we introduced a policy on universal accessibility. This was developed in association with the Arts with the Disabled Association, and it's actually a first. This is we're the first arts organisation to have a formal policy.
We've been trying to introduce new ideas. I mean, first of all, when it comes to wheelchair access, we're trying to go beyond the code and work towards best practice where possible. We've also introduced different ideas. So, for example, movable arm rests, allowing it people to more easily access seats.
Our website also publishes the latest information to help people plan their visit or attendance, and we will continue to monitor the developments in this area very closely. Our watchword, as I said, is the show must go on, but most importantly, it must be done in a safe and comfortable manner for those people who are participating. I'd like
Kingsley, thank you. So I'm going to start by talking about the accessibility service. This is something that is of incredible importance to West Kalund and to society as a whole. Just a background on the development of accessibility services. From 2013, we've been having a large number of stakeholder
As part of our process, we've been having regular stakeholder consultations. We report regularly to the Rehabilitation Advisory Committee. Also, we deal with the Hong Kong Council of Social Services, and we've been inviting local disability groups in to help us with audits to really get information from them about how the.
And we're generally for all our events trying to create an inclusive environment with access services available for various programmes. These might be touch tours, they might be special access provisions, special workshops. And for example, there you see we have an accessible service booth that we have at our.
Our initiatives.
part of the process.
Thank you. Who will be next?
finished? yes.
中心啦，同埋呢一個嘅誒自由空間嘅。
多謝主席。係，阿莊莊小姐。
我 just move on to the next element, which is ticketing services.
rescheduling, we've been able to get in contact with people immediately via email, which has been a really, really beneficial.
for the free space, we've seen seventy-eight percent of tickets sold online, and average across all events, it works out at around forty-six percent.
We have an in-house ticketing system, which is operated under licence. And in this in the last year, we've issued over 150,000 tickets.
Ticket purchase channels include telephone sales, ticket counters, and we also sell through selected Tomlin stores and the Academy Performing Arts.
These outlets like Tomlin in the APA don't represent a huge percentage, but we do keep them because we think it's important to allow more people access to tickets who maybe have limited access to the internet.
and I'm pleased to say we've had recognition for this work internationally. We've won an award in terms of the quality of the work we've done, and the manager of our accessibility team has been invited to speak in the United Kingdom and in Taiwan on.
One of the key features of this is that we charge no service fee for people buying tickets online. We're trying to encourage people to book online wherever possible, but we do have other outlets. Online sales subsequently are growing significantly. For the tea house at the C2C Centre, sixty percent of tickets are sold online.
Running our own ticketing system has allowed us to grow our e-list, so we can communicate directly to people. It has allowed us to understand more about their preferences, to understand more about their booking habits, and particularly in light of the recent situation, it's allowed us to deal efficiently and quickly with refunds and
多謝主席。啊，我跟住會講關於我哋嘅藝術場地嘅。咁其實我哋係個啊，今年係我哋嘅第一年啦，亦都我哋嘅開幕年啦。咁其實開幕年咧係誒，當然大家係非常之興奮嘅，但係亦都係非常之負挑戰性嘅，因為各樣嘅誒元素之下，因為大家都一個新嘅團隊啦。噉我哋喺誒第一年兩個表演藝術場地分別就係戲曲。
Okay.
嗯。
因為，它唔得work。
小型嘅藝團咧，係能夠喺文化區嘅演出。
咧可以嗰個整體個年齡羣同埋嗰個觀眾羣嗰個誒誒平均年齡咧，希望可以去誒拉低啦，同埋吸引啲新觀眾嘅。
噉我哋個誒戲曲中心咧喺誒一月二十號正式開幕啦。噉我哋誒經過三個息三個月嘅誒開幕季啦。咁隨即喺五月咧就開始我哋租用者同埋我哋自己啊西九文化區用嘅誒嘅用途啦。咁而另外我哋嘅戲曲中心誒，另外我哋嘅自由空間咧就喺我哋今年六月咧係正式開幕嘅。
噉佢冇一個特定嘅開幕季，但係亦都有好多唔同嘅開幕嘅誒安排啦。開幕節目嘅安排。咁而我哋誒西九文化區嘅最大嘅特色咧，就係我哋係有呢一個嘅誒誒每一個場地係有佢自己本身嗰個嘅藝術使命嘅，亦都佢哋嘅有一個好好重要嘅藝術主導嘅一個誒。
理念嘅，咁喺呢個理念之下咧，亦都喺一個每一個空間之下咧，我哋係會有一個印度創作啦，根據佢既有嗰個藝術理念去創作啦，同埋增加個演出機會啦，同埋另外另另誒，從而能夠培育更多嘅觀眾，促進呢個文化欣賞嘅。咁而喺我哋嘅藝術租用者，當然因為佢係。
藝術租用者咧，而能夠誒優先預訂我哋個誒檔期啦，同埋付比較誒相宜嘅誒租金嘅。我哋嘅租金收費機制其實分兩個層面，第一個層面咧就係一個比較低嘅門檻啦，咁另外就係同嗰個票房掛鈎啦，係分擔個財務風險嘅。咁而從而咧，亦都可以。
支持比較長期嘅演出，因為一個低門檻咧，就令到佢哋原先喺之前需要啊去投入嘅嗰個資金咧，係相應地係誒減低，亦都將令到嗰個團體咧、藝術團體咧係減低佢哋嘅風險嘅。咁而呢一個嘅機制咧，喺我哋去考慮同埋去推出嘅時候咧，我哋係希望能夠幫助一啲嘅中。
咁而喺呢一段期間，我哋誒自呢一個我哋開幕之到到而家，其實我哋個租用者嘅節目咧，都非常之多元化嘅，亦都係根據我哋嘅誒藝術既定嘅使命咧，去去去揀選我哋不同嘅租用者啦。咁當中我哋當然會有升級嘅節目啦。剛剛誒阿跑做完呢一個嘅帝女花啦，咁當然又話遮佢本身。
嘅演出啦。咁另外好誒誒好重要對於我哋嚟講，就係去涉獵同埋去誒介紹畀香港嘅觀眾咧唔同嘅地方戲曲啦。所以我哋有呢一個嘅誒石劇啦，第一次嚟到香港嘅演出啦。咁亦都有昆劇嘅當中嘅誒表演啦。噉啊特別一提嘅咧，值得一提嘅係本地原。
創嘅節目嘅，亦都係一個首演喺呢一個戲曲中心。呢一個對於我哋嚟講係一個好鼓舞嘅，因為戲曲去做一個原創節目而能夠做二十場咧，係真係誒都係一個創舉嚟嘅。因為即係首演通常你好少話會做一個咁長嘅檔期。咁但係呢一個誒誒花木蘭嘅咪木蘭傳説呢一個誒。
yes.
我哋。
點解？
Thank you.
十八個percent嘅。
啊，佢。
With that facility.
some of the images you can see on the screen is the grand lawn.
O.K. 最後有關壓拍，辯位介紹。
Yeah, thank you. Okay, I'll give you an overview on the art park and the an update on where at.
The Great Lawn, sorry, and the harbour, harbourside lawn. At the moment, we have over 2,000 trees that are planted with a 100 species.
We're finding that the population of the park is growing week on week, and that people are really starting to enjoy the venue and the facilities.
The park and public open spaces are an integral part of the overall development, which will cover 23 hectares of the site when finished.
拋翻上嗰個數字㗎，戲劇佔咗佔大部分嘅五十二嘅percent，誒舞蹈十八，音樂十六，多元藝術十三啦。咁而頭先提到嘅誒故宮博物館裏邊嗰個嘅誒嗰個seminar咧，就係就係嗰個我哋非表演藝術嗰一個percent啦。
劇目咧，佢其實誒採用咗好多嘅新元素啊，包括立體投影啦，包括呢一個虛擬嘅實景咧，一啲好年青人嘅誒先至明白嘅一啲嘅誒誒劇場嘅嘅用法啦。咁而呢一個其實佢最主要嚟講係希望吸引一啲嘅年青嘅新觀眾啦，以至喺睇戲曲嘅朋友。
咁另外，我哋當然誒要去培育嘅誒誒兒童嘅接班人啦。咁所以兒童粵劇亦都喺我哋當中嘅中年者裏邊咧。誒，當我哋睇到佢哋即係三代一齊嚟睇節目嘅時候，或者係去欣賞個孫喺個枱面上嘅節目嘅時候咧，我哋都其實都誒都比較鼓舞嘅，因為誒係係非常之需要一啲新嘅誒。
觀眾啦，同埋表演者咧喺呢一個戲曲呢個層面度嘅咁個誒戲曲中心個使用情況咧，其實喺我哋嘅大劇院咧，喺我哋五月至到誒誒二零二零年嘅三月咧，即係我哋呢一個嘅財政年度裏邊咧，係有誒使用率係佔誒誒佔八十四個percent嘅。咁而喺八十個四個percent裏邊。
咧，由於我哋二零一九年係專注去做翻戲曲嘅表演啦，咁當中嗰個percentage會個高一啲啦，噉就佔咗九十二個誒percent嘅。咁而茶館劇場啦，茶館劇場其實主力咧就係做翻我哋自己誒嘅誒新星節目啦。咁嗰個使用率有七十二個percent啦，而當中咧嗰個戲曲嘅比重咧就係九。
至於話誒自由空間啦，自由空間最大一個場地咧就係我哋大俠啦，嗰個黑俠嘅誒嘅嘅劇場啦。咁而當中由六月至到二零二零年三月呢一個財政年度裏邊咧，佢哋佔咗七十五個percent嘅使用率啦。而當中嘅每一個唔同嘅藝術嘅誒領域咧，就係誒個。
多謝。
On that, I'll hand over to.
要make it the go-to destination.
嗰類嚇，仲有咧亞洲美食。
And this has been also very popular with the local community.
and also the viewing terrace is you know shares magnificent views of Hong Kong Island and the city skyline.
And here is an image of the afternoon sunset, which is becoming a popular destination for people to come and and and view.
咁而家就輪到誒議員發問嘅時間。哦，仲有part，OK，the most important part about the retail, about the food and and the。
We've hosted sixteen events so far. Sorry, fifteen events, six of which West Carlun have physically organised.
We're also focusing on the shared economy. We have the smart bike service in the park, which is a collaboration between ourselves and the Tonghua group of hospitals.
And we continue to operate the park tours and workshops. 26 park tours and workshops have been conducted in 2019, and we will increase that number in in 2020.
喺藝術公園裏邊嘅餐飲咧，啊已經全餐飲嘅鋪位咧已經全部租出去啦，啊同埋咧大部分都已經開始做生意，啊剩翻落嚟少部分咧，亦都喺依幾個禮依兩個禮拜之內咧，應該亦都會開始營業。
attracting over fifty thousand participants, which include include the jazz fest, and pop up markets etc. and we're continuing to build programs and look at ways to engage public and community into the park.
唔該，邊啊？邊位啊？得主席，係係啊！唔該，啊陳生，陳博士，除除西九文啊文化區戲曲中心同埋藝術公園、樂城文作咧啊，其配套嘅餐飲、零售嘅鋪咧都開始啊，相繼開始營業。
late last year we launched the park information booth, which is a mobile visitor information centre, where people can get more information about the parks and the various programmes that are happening, including our performing arts programmes. They can get information from this mobile booth, which travels through the park.
啊！好似就係君君文講啦，七啊，喺公園裏邊嘅餐飲區咧，嚇，其實面對維埃維多利亞港啊個景色就係即係香港嘅好罕有嘅啊。咁公個公園裏邊提供餐飲嘅種類係多元化啊，其中包括有中啊中菜啊，有啊西西餐啊，就唔係意粉啊、披薩。
嗰個月份。
係唔係？
嗯。
咁誒。
多謝各位介紹。咁而家咧就係議員發問嘅時間。啊，首先係啊江俊宇議員。
色嘅飲品，而家嗱年青人好好好喜歡嘅嚇，有嗱糕點、茶，同埋咧同埋戲曲有關嘅小主題嘅小小禮品店啊。
借貸嘅情況如何？會唔會進一步擴大個赤字啦？其次就係M加究竟能唔能夠如期如上次會議所講，今年三月能夠取得入火紙，定還是要有延期咧？先問兩條問題，唔該主席。O.K.邊位回應？啊，Mr. Prescott。
啊，同啊而喺啊氣居中心地下一層同Austin道啊相連嘅商鋪咧，啊就會我哋今年之內都會開始租出，開始招租咧，就希望就係開同埋地啊個通道開開啊唔通開通嗰陣時配合。
inspections statutory inspection process we expect to start this month and it obviously depends on how well that goes but at the moment we're expecting end March April would be about right for securing the op it depends on really
咁特色餐酒酒吧同埋一個特色嘅咖啡廳嚇噉。另外咧嚇，甚至啊，我呢啲啊愛中意狗嘅人士咧，可以同埋嘅嘅愛犬咧一齊去進食嘅嘅輕食嚇，其實係熱狗嚇，所以係係好受歡好受歡迎嘅。希望大家都去啊親自去睇。
嚇，咁戲曲中心咧嚇，裏邊開開嘅嘅嘅鋪頭亦都啊已經商界開業啦。其中包括咗咧有誒粵菜啊潮州潮州菜嘅酒樓嚇，有港式茶餐廳嚇，裏邊嘅公仔麪係有有誒係香港特色嚇，咁亦都有咧啊燒味同埋燉湯店嚇，亦啊特。
啊！嗯，再另外一個咧，就喺我哋個自由空間嘅地下裏邊咧，啊，我哋啲設都設有一個啊，有現場音樂表演啊嘅咖啡廳酒吧嚇噉就令啊可以咧係提供一個可以好輕鬆嘅同埋朋友一齊去欣欣賞音樂嘅地方啊！咁主席嚇就。
啊，早晨，主席。噉啊，當然咧，其實就都大家都好熟㗎啦。我知我好關注咧，就整個西九嗰個嘅即係未來形運。尤其是我之前有講過，就係誒。首先我係非常之關注M加個入夥指嘅進展啦。咁其次就係誒，因為根據誒喺文件所指咧，就啊近半年嘅情況咧就。
不得不調動一啲嘅場地噉，但係我都想必先要提醒咧，之前教咗之前個數字，二零二一至二零二二嘅預計嗰個嘅啊，即係赤字都有三十一億左近嘅，都仲要去借錢噉，想問一問即係局方可唔可以交代一下？首先第一就係而家嗰個最新嗰個嘅虧蝕啊，又或者？
How much the inspectors decide that they want us to modify or amend to comply with the statutory requirements. Having said that, we always anticipated that it would be between nine months and twelve months after the OP before we would be able to open the museum, because frankly, once you have opened
即係。
上蓋咧，佢冇辦法有錢去營運嘅。
但係，我 prefer 去 into 它 in detail at the appropriate time.
As as you see now, is not creating a problem for. Oh, it's a huge problem.
即係玩得到先好謝啊，大佬三啊一億啊！你而家仲要cut，但係我係非常之擔憂。唔該，小靜。
緊卅一億㗎啦，你借錢㗎啦。好啦，我嘅問題係問誒喺而家你嗰個啊M加再拖一拖再拖嘅情況之下，會唔會擴大個赤字面咁解啫？係咪真係冇資料定係點啊？
There's still a huge amount of work that has to go in to fit out the individual spaces, to fit out the office spaces, the gallery spaces, etc. So whether it's March or April, or frankly even into May, won't make too much difference in terms of our opening of the museum towards the end of the year or early next year.
But it will be still on time. Expecting March to yeah. That's that's the timetable we're working to. Okay. About the financial. We'll be coming back with more information on the financial situation of the authority. I believe in April. So we'll deal with that then.
誒，首先第一就誒，僕協唔好介意我追得咁緊，因為我成日覺得咧，即係呢個即係近乎黑洞嘅情況之下咧，僕協作為委員真係要追得好緊嘅。嗱，舊年咧上一次會就話三月，咁而家我聽到最新個即係局方就話啊三月啦、四月啦、啊五月啦噉樣，噉我唔知下次再問嘅時有冇冇停一停，連。
底開同埋年初開咧，睇嚟都係一個非常之大嘅空間啦。但係咧，其實大家都知道啦，一日都搞唔掂呢個M家嘅博物館咧，其實你簡直係即係難以處理。稍後A.C.嗰個即係誒，希望幫佢能夠自己揾翻啲錢啊嘅狀態嗰個，即係起碼都填下債先啦。咁呢個令我好擔心啊，同埋我想問多我。
我想問多少少，追清楚啲。嗱，而家呢一刻係手上未有資料，定未計，定還是其實已經係稍後咩時間會交到嗰個最新嗰個誒赤字有冇變化？因為我相信啦，喺文件裏面有寫啊，過去半年嗱，我想講唔好賴，即係本身你都蝕緊三十一億㗎啦。OK，就或者你虧蝕緊赤字。
啊，秘書長，嗯，我幾句先，然後再啦嚇。誒，首先咧，我諗要澄清一樣嘢咧。誒，喺個加強財務安排嘅時候咧，其實都預見咧。誒，西九管理局咧喺二零年、二零二三、二四左右咧都要借貸嘅。咁所以嗰陣時咧，誒，即係成個安排咧，就係話。
政府係會負擔佢第一期、第二期嘅一啲文化設施嘅興建，同埋一啲誒誒所謂誒公共基誒公共嘅基礎建設。咁有啲嘢咧係西九都要自己去誒，即係處理，譬如話營運嘅開支。咁所以點解就畀咗佢嗰個地嘅誒發展權啊？Under嗰個啊B.O.
嘅嘅嘅安排啦嚇，咁所以其實喺成個結構裏邊咧，西九係去到咁上下時間係要考慮借貸嘅。咁至於嗰個誒誒所謂嘅赤字，嗰赤字係一年即係按一年一年計，因為佢而家基本上咧誒啲地庫誒都未起好啦，咁所以上個嘅發展咧係未能夠完成。
謝謝，跟住係陳志全議員。
嚇！但係當你個使用唔係。
戲曲中心嘅使用啦，我睇翻啲數字，嗯。
戲曲中心自己製作係佔咗一個絕絕大部分㗎，咁未來個方案係咪都係咁咧？唔該。
誒八十四個percent係誒使用率，咁茶館仲低少少七十二，咁呢兩個使用率大家滿滿唔滿意咧？因為
我哋叫fully utilise，即係真係用盡嘅時候，其實都可以容許其他嘅表演項目。即係當年紅磡體育館都唔係體育啦，即係即係今時今時今日，咁所以。
The key is getting that two area two ABC basement sorted out, because that's where most of the commercial elements lie. We need that desperately.
叫做租唔出啦嚇嚇嘅時間，會唔會有啲更更有效嘅運用，或者即係平啲，或者係誒免費啊，畀一啲某一啲團體去使用咧？咁茶館都係啦，茶館而家就係誒。
你裏邊係有場地租用者同埋係管理局自己嘅製作，咁如果見到一個噉嘅空間，係咪管理局會加強誒自己嘅製作，去令到個戲曲中心嗰個使用更加好？定喺啲？
議員係熟路啦，佢就去下一層去，噉就唔使排隊，唔使排隊。但係如果係誒啲，尤其是老人家咯，可能都要排幾長嘅嘅時間嚇，個中場休息未必夠時間去到誒洗手間。咁講翻嗰個誒。
噉佢何來會有經常性嘅收入咧？咁所以喺呢度，我希望呼籲誒各位議員，當我哋稍後時間關於誒嗰個第誒第第二期嘅松two嗰個誒地庫誒嘅項目到到去財委會嘅時候，希望大家儘快批，因為唔批嗰個咧就根本冇辦法發展上。
誒其實啊，Mr. Prescott啊，議員關心同埋擔心係合理嘅。噉我我相信你回應議員個問題咧，最重要嘅咧就係有尺字。噉你認為係一個問題，我哋都理解嘅。但係響之前你預計之內咧，即係而家都係響。
嗰個範圍之內冇令到嗰個情況更差，噉我我我想我相信議員係想知道依一點嘅。咁至於詳細嗰啲數字啊等等咧，咁Mr.Perscott你都講咗咧，你四月會啊比較詳細啲啊畀我哋睇嘅係嘛？補充一句啫，主席一句啫，即係我我想回一回啊，比書長就。
Mr. Chairman, can I just pick up on one point? The ACE project is not contingent on M Plus at all. It's a totally different location. One of the reasons that we can take that forward immediately is because it isn't dependent on the basement development. And I anticipate, assuming that the board approves, that we'll be starting.
the formal tender process this month, so that that project will be moving forward. I'll also be looking at a couple more of the commercial projects, we call 31 and 34, probably by the middle of this year. So we are progressing the commercial side as well as the cultural art side. But quite frankly, as the permanent secretary quite rightly pointed.
係誒唔該，主席。主席其實喺誒戲曲中心同埋自由空間呢兩個場地設施啟用之前咧，我哋已經係西九用家嚟㗎啦，即係我哋咧已經誒book西九嘅空地咧，搞一啲大型活動，搞咗幾年嘅拼多咁個經驗都係整體上都係愉快嘅。不過如果我哋要講，
嘅。
跟住請阿方女士。
and that we will be doing. So perhaps Lisa can comment on that latter part.
Three district councils operate events within the park, and we work with them to sponsor them.
啲租用者去去傾下偈啊、交流下，因為我我聽到嘅你而家唔使答我，即係你翻去處理。我聽到嘅就係有啲人用，即係用就梗係想嚟租用第一次啦，但係租用租用完第一次之後咧，可能都有啲誒。
Mr. Chairman, I'll start and then I'll pass on to my colleague. A couple of things. First, we welcome Pink Dot to come back again as often as it wants. It's a very popular programme, which I have to say we we're very happy that we're working with you on that.
You also mentioned this issue of boosting utilisation rates and offering free accommodation. I'm afraid, you know, coming back to the earlier conversation about our financial situation, that's not an option that I would be very happy to pursue.
講緊個營運情況咧，我覺得未來如果有機會咧，真係可以請一啲用家上嚟誒，去同我哋交流一下。即係除咗觀眾啦，誒可以係場地租用者或者係誒表演者都可以，即係佢哋有第一手嘅經驗咧，可以話畀我哋知。因為淨係我哋，我哋都係使用者。
嘅即係譬如我我都係集中講戲曲中心啦。如果個戲曲中心誒最大嗰個意見，我個個去完都係㗎啦。唔知你哋點樣解決到？就係中場休息嘅時間咧，去廁所，尤其是係女性去廁所咧，真係仍然都一個好好睏擾大家嘅問題嚟嘅。即係我哋上次睇大女花，咁陳淑莊。
嗰個誒大劇院就係八十四個percent，茶館咧就係七十二個percent。咁首先我想知就係誒非戲曲嘅使用係而家係有八個percent啦嚇。噉係可唔可以講係包括啲乜嘢係非戲曲使用？因為過去我哋就話戲曲優先咧，戲曲中心當然。
In terms of users and others that we want to interact, we heard in the earlier presentation the work that we're doing with membership, but we also have our consultation panel which we reach out and through that we've brought in district councils, for example. Each year for the last two years we've had.
where where where we are looking is perhaps to do joint programming, where we will absorb the cost of the operation of of a theatre in conjunction with with a partner. But frankly, there is always a cost. There's no such thing as a free theatre. Someone has to pay for it either ourselves or or.
But we obviously do look at that, and in terms of boosting utilisation rates, particularly in C2, after this first year where we gave an undertaking to give priority almost exclusively to the C2 users, now that we're into the second year, of course, it gives us a bit more flexibility to look at other users.
啊，sorry，阿莊莊女士，多謝主席，多謝陳議員嘅提問。誒，關於個誒戲曲中心大劇院同埋茶館劇場嗰個嘅用途咧，其實喺我哋嗰個誒誒第一年二零一九年咧，我哋應承咗戲曲業界咧係淨係做戲曲嘅，咁所以咧嘅嗰個戲曲嘅用量咧係比較相應第。
係比較多嘅，其實九十幾個percent係非常之咁高嘅。咁講翻個大劇院先，大劇院裏邊咧嗰八十四個percent裏邊咧，九十二個percent係戲曲啦。咁其他個六個percent其實係我哋嘅誒多元藝術嘅，其實音樂劇係我哋自己嘅誒大狀王嚟嘅。咁另外嗰誒兩個percent咧就係戲劇，而戲劇咧就喺二零二零年開始。
嗯。
啊，Lisa有嘢補充。
誒，跟住係黃碧雲議員。
主席就誒有幾個問題想問啦，就誒關於嗰個而家我哋有誒藝術公園開咗啦，咁呢度又講睇日落好靚啦噉。
有發翻一個問卷畀佢哋咧，係令到佢哋去話翻畀我聽，有乜嘢我哋誒有進步嘅空間啦，又有啲咩做得好，有啲唔好嘅，亦令到我哋本身呢個咁新嘅團隊咧，都有可以對症下藥咯。咁多謝你嘅提問。
好遠可以行得到入去西九呢一個公園嗰度咧，咁因為而家我哋啲天橋未未博好啊，咁冇之前咧，我哋而家要用政府現有嘅嗰啲天橋，嗰啲天橋亦都冇，有啲係冇電梯嘅。
and that's why it's equally important for us to be getting that feedback to adjust the way we operate to respond to the to the needs of our clients and yes I absolutely agree with you that is something we must not just do now but continue to do as we open more venues.
因為喺二零零二零二零二零年開始咧，我哋係可喺戲曲中心度係容許有不同嘅藝術嘅類別咧，去用嗰個戲曲中心嘅大劇院啦，同埋呢個茶館劇場嘅。咁而茶館劇場啦，因為誒我哋自己本身嘅新星節目咧，著實我哋嗰個使用率咧會係着重咗喺呢一個呢一方面嘅。咁而呢個節
一日一一個星期大概做七至九場度啦，咁睇下有冇呢個學生場啦。咁其實嗰個智力咧係去誒，其實軟件嗰度有提到㗎啦。其實智力去發展翻新嘅觀眾啦，嚇畀一啲新嘅唔同嘅觀眾去去嘗試去認識呢個戲曲啦。咁同埋亦都係希望有啲學生專場咧，令到學生對我哋自己本本土。
嗰個傳統文化咧係有更多嘅認識嘅，咁所以戲曲中心裏邊嘅茶館劇場咧，其實個個主力咧係會做翻呢一個節目嘅。咁剩翻星期一、二咧，我哋就會睇翻啲誒唔同嘅類別咧，可以去租用呢一個空間咯。主席可唔可以畀我講多兩句意見？就係誒，我唔知你哋會唔會之後時候會同啲用家即係長。
唔係幾好，或者唔係幾滿意嘅感覺噉就啊，下次可能翻翻去文誒藝術中心啊，或者文化中心啊。咁呢啲我諗你係應該要即係聽到聽下多啲佢哋意見，睇下點樣去改善戲曲中心，即係唔好淨係變成一個即係大家嚟幫襯一次，即係就誒未必會將你變成首選嘅一個場地啦。唔該。
Yes, Mr. Chairman. In fact, as we heard earlier, we do surveys among our audience, but we also follow up with all of our users, the hirees of the venue, to understand if there are issues. So far, generally, the feedback has been very positive. Of course, with a new venue starting up, you're learning all the time.
喂，誒，我想誒誒去去回應翻呢一個提問。其實呢個非常之好嘅提問嚟嘅，因為其實我哋好重視我哋去誒每一位用家咧，其實就特別係租用者咧，對於我哋每一樣唔同嘅服務咧，係有咩嘅嘅誒反應啊、回饋嘅。咁其實我哋喺早前已經同啊百和咧坐底做咗一個好詳盡。
嘅誒誒嘅嘅嘅大會嘅噉，大家就住每一個point，佢哋去提出嘅咧，我哋都有一個嘅誒誒不同嘅誒回應畀佢哋啦。咁嗰個對於我哋嚟講係一個大家互相嘅一個誒學習嘅嘅誒嘅機會嚟嘅。咁另外，我哋其實喺啊，我哋好多嘅租用者裏邊，我哋其實。
咁誒，大家亦都喺嗰個場地嗰個通達設施嗰度，即係我相信場內已經誒做得好好嘅。根據你附件一嗰度所講，噉我比較擔心咧，就係誒如何引領到啲市民去到呢一個地方，咁即係話咧。
其實，如果我哋只係睇西九裏邊做到幾好咧，如果你出邊冇配合咧，其實都係有問題嘅。噉我就希望常備可以幫下手咧，即係我諗要誒要注意一下咧，就係誒嗰個交通嘅接駁，因為其實去到藝術公園嗰邊都幾吊腳嘅，即係。
即係誒市民點樣點樣誒坐車去得到嗰度咧，或者點樣行路可以行得到去咧？咁如果坐輪椅嗰啲或者推住B B車嗰啲，應該點去得到嗰度？咁呢度其實而家係都幾幾困難嘅。咁所以我諗一諗咧，就係話嗰個誒交通配套嗰度有冇嘢可以改？
線噉，我最近都試過咧，就喺九龍站搭嘅七十四號小巴咧，佢而家係開咗一個stop咧，就停咗喺誒西九公園出邊。咁咁嗰度係可以去到嘅。咁但係個問題就係，如果我哋喺佐敦嗰邊過嚟嘅，佢坐七七十四號，佢嚟到九龍站停咗咯喎，佢唔可以，即係佢佢佢要。
可能再再要落車再上車，噉佢先至可以去得到西九個公園嗰個站嘅。咁即係話其實有冇其他嘅誒專線小巴或者即係shuttle bus可以安排到佢哋可以喺譬如佐敦或者尖沙咀，佢哋可以直接嚟得到誒西九公園咧？咁咁呢個要同運輸署個。
藝術公園。
做啲咩手術？
我係Mr.Pescar。
要被採取由相關主管機關。
As far as the car parking spaces, there are around.
咁其實亦都冇冇parking space畀誒啲市民可以去，佢就全部要圍泊曬喺路邊嘅。
咁咁點搞咧？咁噉我知道咧。我最近去過咧，就係見到誒，可能有活動，就好多人自己揸車去，就喺西九個公園出邊咧，拍曬喺路邊。
邊夾一夾咁？另外咧就係誒，如果喺誒元芳嗰邊，或者九龍站嗰邊，或者高鐵站嗰邊，佢哋想行過嚟西九，佢有即係嗰邊嘅指示牌其實就唔好足夠嘅，即係點樣行係誒？有冇一啲無障礙嘅通道可以好便捷，唔使兜？
噉我都唔知道，究竟西九會唔會？你哋都有一啲地方係可以考慮埋，係有公眾嘅parking，畀佢哋容易便捷啲入到公園咧。因為我見到好多係帶住小朋友誒去公園嗰度嘅V.N.，咁而家咧就係好多違泊啦。咁呢啲係我觀察到，即係去現場睇到，即係遇到嘅困。
嗱，咁另外一個咧就係單車嗰度，單車得五十部，其實夠唔夠咧？同埋點解係要同東華山醫院合作嘅咧？係咪因為嗰個管理維修單車啊？因為係收錢嘅問題。咁而家呢個收費係收幾多嘅咧？咁咁誒，即係呢啲我即係我覺得有單車係好嘅，即係對於公園裏邊咁最。
仲有一個咧，就關於噪音嘅問題啦。咁咧，我係即係好歡迎你有啲户外嘅活動，有啲誒music嘅。咁但係即係我唔知你有冇諮詢過，或者問一問九龍站上邊屋苑，因為其實好近嘅。噉我最近就誒喺HarbourView Place，即係天際嗰邊，其實就好近你哋嗰個公開表演場。
場度見到你好多燈喺嗰度flash，即係喺個tunnel個口嗰度。咁噉，但係個問題真係室內，即使有雙重玻璃咧，都係感覺到個base係好勁，嘣嘣嘣嘣，間屋係震緊，係感覺到嘅。噉我唔知你哋會唔會同表演嗰啲單位傾傾，究竟有啲咩方法可以令到減少嗰個噪？
I'll pass on to to Graham and perhaps the PM set can also comment. First of all, we are gradually increasing the number of minibus and in fact franchised bus routes to connect to the district. There are, I believe, at the moment, two different minibus routes and one franchised bus route that comes in to.
And we're constantly working with transport department to see how we can further improve that. But quite frankly, the solution is to get the Arthur Square Bridge built, because that will dramatically improve access from Elements, and that is clearly the transport interchange. So again, I would urge members to support the application for that.
bridge because it really does transform accessibility to the district. Beyond that, we're also we have support from government to look at putting in ferry piers, and I think that would be a very very valuable additional route to connect us with the rest of Hong Kong, particularly across the harbour.
We're also looking at the parking issue. The situation that you may have observed on the road of illegal parking is not because there is a shortage of parking. It's because people are not prepared to pay the parking rates. A lot of those people are workers, for example, working on Mplus or the Palace Museum site, who choose to drive but refuse.
好。
noise。
within the the parameters of the noise legislation in Hong Kong, and some people are simply more sensitive than others. But all of our shows must comply with the relevant noise legislation in Hong Kong. I'm sorry, perhaps Permsec might might want to comment on the transport and then Graham.
儘快可以將呢啲工程上馬，噉我亦都記得咧，議員係去年咧係提出嘅話，亦都希望有啲渡輪嘅服務。咁而家咧係其實係亦都係研究緊咧喺誒西九海旁嗰條路咧，喺唔同嘅地方咧係會容許咗啲位咧係可以做一啲誒誒渡輪嘅接駁。
Apart, we've recently been taking action under our facilities management team to crack down on that. And if you go today, I would be very surprised if you see any illegal parking on the site because of that action. And of course, once the road is handed over back to government and it becomes a government road, we would expect that enforcement action.
兩百六十available， which except for the most busy times at weekends， more than adequate to cope for the demand that that there is. There is in addition to standard car parking spaces， there are charging spots for electric vehicles and of course disabled parking as well.
In addition to that, we make available parking at our own office buildings at weekends to boost the number of car park spaces, so that we are trying to provide as much space as we can. But yes, I mean illegal parking is an issue, and that's something we're trying to address definitely. As far as the smart bike and issues along.
This is something that we do actually have regular contact with the owners corporation from the buildings around us. It is something that we in fact notify them when there will be an outdoor event in the park. But it is a fact of life that, as far as we can, we do try to work.
李主席，好誒，多謝黃碧雲議員嚇。首先咧，誒，其實黃碧雲議員咧都好關心個通達性嘅。譬如喺上次會咧，你講個無障礙嘅升降機啊，同埋誒停車場等等咧，其實我哋都同有關部門咧係跟進緊，有啲甚至係做緊可行性研究。我亦都知道有啲同事咧亦都同你見過面嘅嚇。
噉就住嗰個整體通達性咧，其實運輸署喺二零零九年咧已經完成咗西九龍新發展區嘅詳細交通研究嘅。咁咧誒喺誒，我記得係誒前幾次會咧，亦都有一次好詳細嘅討論嘅。咁亦都咧係誒，我哋會將提供一連串嘅行人天橋，包括頭先啊柏志高。
先生講嗰個誒誒誒藝術天橋嚇藝術天橋啦，誒會連接周邊嘅噉，我哋亦都會係進一步改善港鐵柯士甸道同埋戲曲中心之間嘅行人連接啦，同埋亦都會利用先前興建柯士甸站暫時預留嘅位咧，喺該站嘅地下通道咧會提供一組行。
好現有嘅設施啊！
先生咧，你你就住依個問題都回應一下。
整一啲臨時停車場或者乜嘢，咁令到佢唔會係變成非法嘅泊車咯。
同埋西九站同埋周圍嘅嗰啲泊車位咧，係好多泊唔滿嘅，好多時都泊唔滿嘅。
Yeah, Mr. Chairman, the two hundred and sixty odd spaces are already commissioned. Okay, we know that people are not using them because they're parking on the road, but there are still spaces within the car park. We know that these are people who are simply not prepared to pay. What is it? Sixty dollars a day?
連人嘅連接系統咧，係去到誒戲曲中心嘅地庫嘅。咁亦都咧，我哋係誒誒，其實好希望咧，誒我又要講翻咧，希望嗰個地庫第二層嘅工程咧，盡快撥款，因為點解咧？大家記得咧，誒地面係唔會行車㗎嘛，喺地底噉，即係話將來啲巴士啊、旅遊巴咧個停泊其實就喺地。
付嘅噉，所以咧，其實最終咧，個通達性嘅嘅提升，大力嘅提升咧，係真係要視乎個地庫嘅嘅建立嘅。咁現時咧，其實公眾咧可以利用路面嘅誒公共交通係來往西九嘅。咁西九而家咧有三十多條嘅巴士線同埋係綠色專營小巴嘅。咁另外咧，亦都有誒。
我知道咧喺九龍站咧係有個巴士喺個車度，誒喺M架展亭嗰度附近嘅。咁但係我明白而家困惑，因為我自己本人咧都由佐敦站、九龍站、柯士甸站係用腳行過去嘅。我明白你講話係個signage嗰啲指示唔係好清晰嚇。個原因咧就因為佢而家咧基本上係未起曬。
咁所以去到某一橛咧，你其實係進入一個地盤嘅環境嘅。咁所以我諗呢一個咧係即係暫時咧，我哋係會盡量去做啦。所以點解誒由誒元芳嗰度博過去嗰條嘅藝術天橋係咁重要就係咁解啦。嚇咁所以誒誒，我哋希望即係喺誒個地庫嗰個批准咗之後咧，盡
啊，主主席啊，即係頭頭先我提嗰個所謂誒圍拍嘅問題咧，咁當然我歡迎你做一啲誒措施啦。咁但係你就係打擊圍拍咧就冇用嘅，即係點解會有人圍拍咧？就係有拍車嘅需求啊嘛，即係有demand喺度。咁而家你係冇supply，咁所以我想問清楚頭先柏子。
高話有二百幾個泊車位，其實嗰啲係喺邊咧咁噉，因為而家咧我哋知道有好多工程未完嘅噉，但係art park嗰邊O K啦嘛，咁所以嗰邊其實係即係有冇有冇泊車嘅位可以令到啲人可以去到嗰邊，噉就變咗鼓勵多啲人去到海旁或者係即係用到。
我理解正話嗰個即係正話啊，官方答咗咧，就係話而家嗰啲違例泊車咧，就唔係用緊西九措施嘅人嚟嘅，就係外邊其他嘅使用者嚟嘅。咁但係當然啦，如果越嚟越多人使用依個西九文化區嘅咧，泊車位嘅需求係。
高嘅噉。主席其實唔係嘅，我去現場觀察嗰啲人係泊喺路邊，係行入藝術公園嘅，係行入arts park嘅，因為嗰度有個大草地有啲活動。咁we end係有啲family帶啲人去嗰邊嘅。噉啊，咁但係就就就啲車唔知停曬，唔知應該可以停喺邊啦。咁西九會唔會有一啲地可以？
誒主席，我誒誒誒誒，或者我提供啲資料啦。喺鄰近嘅泊車位嘅供應咧，而家海港城係有二千個，中港城三百五十個，銅鑼總會五百個，九龍站係誒超過係一千一百個。咁喺九龍西鐵總站咧，亦都有五百個嘅。咁而家西九亦都設有兩個旅遊車上客。
上落客同埋係做短期嘅停車之用嘅，一個就喺地庫一層啦，喺誒誒設喺元芳嘅對面有二十六個位嘅，咁誒另外一個咧就係靠近香港故宮文化博物館同埋A.C發展組合就提供咗十七個嘅，咁呢個咧就當然咧係誒可能都係未夠嘅，咁所以咧我哋都希
希望咧，誒誒誒喺附近咧，其實譬如話道華街誒個停地下停車場亦都可以有七十個箱位嘅，咁亦有三十個私家泊位，同埋有三十。啊，主席啊，我諗唔使唔使上比數白攬啊，因為而家係講緊靠近藝術公園嗰邊有冇泊停啊嘛，你同我數道華路，你同我。
到童軍，你如果喺童軍嗰度泊完車，你叫啲小朋友老人家行過去公園，我諗行死佢哋啦，即係冇可能。我我諗我哋唔好就住依個問題拗啦，即係依個咧嗱，我我我用我嘅經驗嚟到同大家分享一下。我成日都去嗰個誒西九文化區。
already at an advanced stage of planning for. We had hoped to put a temporary promenade in, but unfortunately, because we we've been encouraged to.
current circumstances, I'm focusing on programmes, not destination, because that's what people will come to see. And I think as more people become familiar
Through things like jazzfests, through things like the free space festivals, then more people are aware how to get to the site. But I agree with you, and we will be doing more at the appropriate time to publicise the site.
誒秘書長，誒主席多謝，想講一句啫。其實喺誒西九文化區咧，誒計劃嘅車位咧係大概有二千三百個嘅，而二千三百個裏邊咧係有千六個。
去嗰度又去食下嘢啊之類之類，即係有冇有啲嘅嘢咧去刺激下嗰邊嘅地方，令到嗰個個地方咧多啲多啲人去嗰度聚集咧？係咪先？係，Mr. Pesco。Good luck in the marathon, by the way.
會喺展覽中心同埋綜合地庫第二期嘅，咁所以個綜合地庫第二期嘅興建咧，係對於嗰個車位嘅提供係一個非常大嘅比例嚟嘅。咁所以點解嗰個係咁重要同埋咁急切啊？
噉啊，當然我哋而家都誒提倡，我哋多啲運動，多啲行路。噉你話一定要去到門口先落車嘅咧，有陣時係有啲困難嘅。咁但係啊啊，黃議員提出嗰啲咧，如果有啲長者係要去嗰度啊，想去行下嘅。
咁或者有冇一啲落車位，你可以提供畀佢哋。噉啊，我諗依依啲都係一個大家應該關注嘅問題嚟嘅。噉啊，咁有二百幾個未起好，咁而家係亦都係唔使用得。咁當然咧，嗰個就係響中心、響西九文化區裏邊嚟嘅。咁所以我都想啊，柏志高。
Sixty dollars a day, and they're still not prepared to pay. So we know from the fact that we have less than half used in the car park space that these are people choosing not to spend that that money and preferring to to park illegally. So the figures speak for themselves. Those two hundred plus are already open and already operational, and they.
佢係右邊，係咪啊？係啊，
試咗條新路咧，就跑入去呢個誒西九文化區。咁咧就誒以前咧就跑到喜谷中心嘅啫。原來我後來發覺到開咗之後咧就跑入去，雖然個難度好大，因為好多地盤啊、好多工友啊噉樣。但係咧即係跑咗去咧係好靚嘅，即係講真事實咧真係好好開心咧有個噉嘅新嘅地區。噉啊啱啱我早兩個禮拜去完新加坡咧，睇到新加坡嗰個即係哈巴芬又係差唔。
多噉，我都希望日後咧，即係一條噉樣好暢達嘅地方，成個由尖旺區、尖沙咀都有個新嘅，即係新嘅改變啦。我我感覺咧都係會一個好好靚嘅地方。不過咧，即係睇現時咧，似乎咧，即係好多市民咧都仍然即係一般普羅市民都未知道嗰個點嘅，即係咧其實咧同埋去嘅誒。
難度咧係喺度嘅，講真，即係我自己跑噉啊跑入去都都有難度。就即係Evan揸車咧，你叫啲人其實琴日咧，我先喺氣谷中心食完飯，噉我先同我啲屋企人咧講啊，不如我哋又去西九文化區行下啦。跟住佢就同我講唔得㗎，個停車場咧就話要行十五分鐘先行到入去㗎。噉啊，跟住拍喺街咧有好多車啊，咁即係仲有好多人咧，我唔知道係咪事實。
啊！但係啲同學好多人咧，仲係呢個觀感，即係覺得咧去嗰度咧係有難度嘅。噉我哋而家嚟緊西九文化區，仲有一段時間先係會即係哇全面開通曬啊！噉樣咁喺呢幾年，我哋都想我哋啲鋪頭啊，又可以生存得到啊，又各樣㗎嘛。咁所以咧，即係我我第一個建議，我都希望咧，即係頭先頭先啊啊主席都有講到話，即係。
停車位嗰度特別，原來嗰個啲人唔肯泊入停車場嘅，可唔可以減租咧？即係減平啲，收平啲嗰個時時租或點？你都想吸引佢入去泊啫嘛？你咪咩泊買滿咩級車停車級費，諸如此類下嗰啲咪得咯？即係我覺得可以諗多啲嘅。其實我啱啱上個禮拜又去咗另一個喺誒學誒誒。
即係誒誒，海濱嗰個新嗰個商場好多人㗎喎，哇！多人到爆曬棚，所有食市都爆曬。咁其實即係我覺得有有一定嘅消費力喺度嘅。其實即係我哋好希望，但係佢哋係一一一一一一棚嘢一齊㗎嘛。但係你而家喺西九文化區嗰度係零零細細嗰舊。如果你你要去令到啲人去咧，你一定要諗啲方法咧，係吸引佢去嘅。
咁呢個呢個係第一啦，即係都提一提。第二咧就係咧，即係而家啲旅遊業都真係差嘅，即係會唔會你哋都嚟緊嗰半年咧，即係有啲嘢係可以同誒，即係啲酒店啊、相關嘅酒店啊、鋪頭啊，大家一齊有啲聯營嘅嘢搞下咧，即係特別喺啲酒店嗰度，即係咁多間好靚嘅酒店喺嗰度，可唔可以鼓勵佢哋啲即係住喺裏邊啲住宿啲人又又？
As far as accessibility, in due course we'll have over 2.3 kilometres waterfront from Canton Road right the way up and round past the Palace Museum. Obviously, again, it depends on funding for the basement to do that central section, but that will make a huge difference. It really will, and that's that's something we're we're all
咁誒？
一啲地方嘅設計嘅。
誒誒，攞多啲生意嘅，咁誒，而且。
依啲非法嘅誒泊車咧，應該去去處理嘅，依個。
誒，我我都同意嘅，因為我都由開始到而家咧，我都好留意整個西九文化區嘅發展嘅。
佢誒車位啊，誒或者其他嘅地方嗰個發展，同埋亦都更改咗。
噉我喺籌備依個西江文化區嗰陣時，作為董事啦，第一屆嘅誒董事啦，噉我都好瞭解到。
啊，雖然而家啊都有一啲好直接嘅啊交通工具可以去到嗰度，但係始終落咗車之後咧，有好多地方咧都係日曬雨淋嘅。
噉，譬如喺一啲避雨亭啊等等依一方面，啊，你哋啊，可可唔可以都誒睇多睇多一啲？你話如果係誒老人家啊，或者誒，
小朋友啊，或者甚至有啲人推埋B B車去嘅，咁即係避雨嘅地方咧，我覺得都要考慮一下，因為嗰度都幾誒好多地方咧都係冇買遮頭嘅，咁或或者啊秘書長啊。
教生意情況點樣樣？咁正話阿鄭議員亦都提出過，喂，可唔可以誒？依個停車場同佢哋有一啲合作啊，去食一個晚餐，可以有一啲免費泊車啊等等。咁依啲都可以幫助到佢哋去。
Mr. Passcott響呢一方面都可以睇一睇嚇。噉我覺得你話如果乜嘢都全面嘅咧，你正話咧擔心個赤字啦。噉我都唔想擔心你個赤字。不過如果你話有啲收入可以幫補嘅，即係例如好似飲食啊、商店啊，畀一啲優惠啊，咁都希望你考慮一下係。
而家即係寧靜嘅地方咧，有可能都比較比較難揾㗎。噉你話如果喺嗰度泊咗車，去到嗰度可以食個晚餐，周圍行下咧，都係一個畀我哋香港市民一個好去處嚟嘅。咁響響呢一方面，我都希望你哋可以考慮一下。咁另外一樣咧，就係。
Use waterfront instead of the roads for all of that material from the site. We we can't do that, but that is part of the plan definitely. As far as the accessibility issue is concerned, we are actually looking at at changing prices. In fact, the sixty dollars a day rate is a concessionary rate.
which we've been selling particularly to workers on the M Plus site and the Palace Museum site, so that they don't park illegally on the roads. And then we're enforcing that through the illegal parking enforcement. As far as the hotel and and other potential partners, yes, indeed, we are working with them through.
The concierge's. We're working with the Hong Kong Tourism Board to again focus on the district as a as a destination. And I agree with you entirely. I think we need to really enhance our the awareness of the district. However, I'll be quite frank with you under the.
至於泊位嗰度咧，我正話都講啦，周圍我都成日去嘅，噉我亦都知道泊位係充足嘅。咁如果有咁多違例嘅泊車，噉我覺得政府方面咧應該向警察方面咧啊投訴嚇，警察要嚴正執法嚇，如果。
誒不但只係阻到行人，亦都阻住交通嘅。咁誒，我我都想有一個好短嘅問題，因為發展區裏邊咧，而家都誒開始或者越嚟越多一啲誒餐廳啊，一啲鋪頭啦開幕啦。咁誒，我我都想了解一下佢哋。
啊！
而家睇下得唔得先。
噉啊！
有冇其他？
少講到有關呢個問題㗎啦。
有冇其他嘅問題？
議員有咩其他嘅問題或者建議？
十三號，係係啊！啊，出個通告，好似你未報名係嘛？
唔係，誒有好多都話誒會報名嘅，係啊，咁OK，咁誒。
第二個咧就係西九文化區藝術家旅舍公寓最新嘅發展。
如果冇咧，噉我哋係啦，噉我哋就啊預期下一個禮拜一，我哋就會啊去西九文化區參觀嘅，係啦，咁多謝曬各位。
誒所謂個個活動啊、行程啊等等咧，我哋都係同你哋聯絡緊嘅。咁希希望你誒，希望嗰日天公做美啊！嚇咁咧，就我哋可以可以。
響現場解答到好多我哋過去咁多次委員會大家提出嘅問題，咁誒我哋亦都會誒公開畀其他嘅委員非呢個西九誒委員會嘅委員參加嘅，噉就誒。
會繼續去去考慮呢樣嘢嘅。嗯。啊。O.K. 好。咁誒，呢個以前咧就到此為止。噉我哋有一個其他事項，我我都誒邀請你哋幾位可以一齊參加嘅。咁呢個咧就係正話阿柏志高先先生咧，都已經誒。
誒提出咗一個邀請，就請我哋啲議員去嗰度參參觀嘅。咁誒，我哋而家誒定咗咧，就係下個禮拜一上晝嘅，我哋就八點四十五分鐘喺依度起程嘅。噉就誒，亦都有一有關一啲誒參觀嘅。
好啊！啊，讓轉啊，主啊，主席係啊，我記得陳生。啊，而家我哋應已經係有個停車優惠呢樣嘢㗎啦。啊，即係去食去食飯嘅話，已經去吸到飛就我哋就免費停車㗎啦。啊，咁當然就係講個啊落雨避雨嗰個問題咧，其實都係好現實嘅問題嚟嘅。啊，啲講話噉，我哋都會都會都。
係啦，下次三月三十會議咧，就將會響三月三十誒星期一嘅下晝四點半至六點半舉行嘅。噉就有兩個討論項目，一個就係西港文化區與鄰近地區融合嘅連接。其實正話，我哋都有些。
警察姐姐。
誒其他事項，議員想提出冇，噉我就宣佈今日嘅會議結束。多謝各位。